[
    {
        "question": "The first pioneers of painting in Kazakhstan who initiated a painting studio in 1920.",
        "options": ["N. Khludov", "A. Kasteyev", "N. Gayev", "G. Ismailova", "E. Mergenov"],
        "answer": "N. Khludov"
    },
    {
        "question": "Author of 'Kyz-Zhibek' opera",
        "options": ["Yevgeny Brusilovsky", "Latif Khamidi", "Gaziz Zhubanov", "Abai", "Mukan Tulebayev"],
        "answer": "Yevgeny Brusilovsky"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Soviet Union time, the Kazakh epic novel, which has become an 'encyclopedia of Kazakh people's life'...",
        "options": ["Red Arrow", "Unhappy Zhamal", "Botagoz", "The Path of Abai", "Urker"],
        "answer": "The path of Abai"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is 'nightingale of Kazakh music'?",
        "options": ["Bibigul Tulegenova", "Amre Kashaubaev", "Ermek Serkebayev", "Rosa Baglanova", "Maria Mudryak"],
        "answer": "Bibigul Tulegenova"
    },
    {
        "question": "Title of the war novel where Baurdzhan Momysh-Uly was a main hero",
        "options": ["Volokolamsk highway", "War psychology", "Kambar-batyr", "Khakarman - Hero", "Moscow is behind us"],
        "answer": "Volokolamsk highway"
    },
   {
        "question": "Leading style in modern costume design in Kazakhstan",
        "options": ["ethnic", "American", "European", "African", "mythological"],
        "answer": "ethnic"
    },
    {
        "question": "Internationalization of capital, the international division of labour, the development and distribution of information technologies are basis for....",
        "options": ["globalization", "development", "universalism", "unification", "transformation"],
        "answer": "globalization"
    },
    {
        "question": "Types of Kazakh culture nowadays",
        "options": ["known and unknown", "elite and high", "mass culture and low", "subculture", "dominant"],
        "answer": "known and uknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "The qualities, beliefs, personality traits, appearance, and/or expressions that characterize a person or group…",
        "options": ["identity", "personality", "individuality", "uniqueness", "originality"],
        "answer": "identify"
    },
    {
        "question": "The idea about the formation and extending of the relationship and interdependence of countries in different regions of the world in various fields (economics, finance, informatics, advanced technologies...)",
        "options": ["globalization", "modernization", "pragmatism", "intercultural communication", "freedom"],
        "answer": "globalization"
    },
  {
        "question": "Annual action in Kazakhstan dedicated to the International Museum Day (18 May) called…",
        "options": ["New life", "Cultural Heritage", "Mangilik El", "Boloshak", "Night at the museum"],
        "answer": "Night at the museum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Examples of cultural institutions",
        "options": ["schools, universities, colleges", "museums, libraries, art galleries", "political, organizational", "houses, mazars, graves", "statutes, banks, companies"],
        "answer": "museums, libraries, art galleries"
    },
    {
        "question": "New trend in delivering the materials in museums",
        "options": ["information technologies", "exhibitions", "new types of museum", "new forms"],
        "answer": "information technologies"
    },
    {
        "question": "New method of delivering the materials in museums",
        "options": ["touch screen", "transformation into a contact space", "exhibitions", "statue", "archives"],
        "answer": "transformation into a contact space"
    },
    {
        "question": "Creation of the Museum of History of Mining and Smelting in the village Zhezdy in the Karaganda region example of …initiative",
        "options": ["personal", "collective", "group", "State", "governmental"],
        "answer": "personal"
    },
   {
        "question": "Who introduced term 'Culture shock'?",
        "options": ["Kalervo Oberg", "Leslie White", "Auguste Komte", "Charles Pierce", "Roland Barth"],
        "answer": "Kalervo Oberg"
    },
    {
        "question": "Equal respect to various cultures in a society, promoting cultural diversity and cultural differences",
        "options": ["multiculturalism", "modernization", "ethnocentrism", "universalism", "pragmatism"],
        "answer": "multiculturalism"
    },
    {
        "question": "What determines the meaning of the existence of a particular people, ethnic group or nation?",
        "options": ["national idea", "goal", "idea", "philosophy", "State"],
        "answer": "national idea"
    },
    {
        "question": "National idea of Kazakhstan",
        "options": ["Mangilik El", "cultural superiority", "freedom and equality", "World superiority", "construction of communism"],
        "answer": "Mangilik El"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who introduced the concept of glocalization?",
        "options": ["R. Robertson", "Ch. Morris", "L. White", "E. Tylor", "F. Saussure"],
        "answer": "R. Robertson"
    },
  {
        "question": "Accelerating the pace of economic development of the republic and improving the quality of life of the population through the use of digital technologies",
        "options": ["100 new faces of Kazakhstan", "Rukhani Zhagyru", "Digital Kazakhstan", "Tugan zher", "Sacraldy Kazakhstan"],
        "answer": "Digital Kazakhstan"
    },
    {
        "question": "Areas of the 'Digital Kazakhstan' program implementation include ...",
        "options": ["competitiveness", "transition to a digital state", "pragmatism", "switch to Latin", "open knowledge"],
        "answer": "transition to a digital state"
    },
    {
        "question": "Main direction of the 'Digital Kazakhstan' program implementation",
        "options": ["digitalization of economic sectors", "knowledgeable society", "pragmatism", "switch to Latin", "open knowledge"],
        "answer": "digitalization of economic sectors"
    },
    {
        "question": "Main direction of the 'Digital Kazakhstan' program implementation",
        "options": ["competitiveness", "development of human capital", "pragmatism", "transition to Latin", "open knowledge"],
        "answer": "development of human capital"
    },
    {
        "question": "When the 'Digital Kazakhstan' program introduced?",
        "options": ["2017", "2018", "2020", "2015", "2016"],
        "answer": "2017"
    },
    {
        "question": "Emergence of Astana IT University belongs to the direction of the 'Digital Kazakhstan' program...",
        "options": ["Digitalization of economic sectors", "Transition to a digital state", "Implementation of the Digital Silk Road", "Development of human capital", "Creating an innovation ecosystem"],
        "answer": "Development of human capital"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to ICT Development Index Kazakhstan in 2016 among 175 countries took place…",
        "options": ["52", "163", "90", "30", "25"],
        "answer": "52"
    },
    {
        "question": "Terms of the program 'Digital Kazakhstan' implementation",
        "options": ["2018-2022", "2017-2021", "2020-2025", "2016-2020", "2015-2020"],
        "answer": "2018-2022"
    },
  {
    "question": "IT sector in Kazakhstan under control by ministry of…",
    "options": [
      "Education and Science",
      "Culture and Sport",
      "Digital Development, Innovations and Aerospace Industry",
      "Finance and Economics",
      "Agriculture"
    ],
    "answer": "Digital Development, Innovations and Aerospace Industry"
  },
  {
    "question": "Minister for Digital Development, Innovations and Aerospace Industry of the Republic of Kazakhstan",
    "options": [
      "Bagdat Musin",
      "Marat Akhmetzhanov",
      "Sayasat Nurbek",
      "Margulan Seysembayev",
      "Askhat Aimagambetov"
    ],
    "answer": "Bagdat Musin"
  },
  {
    "question": "What doesn't belong to the principles of Mangilik El idea?",
    "options": [
      "Kazakh language development",
      "Patriotism and unity",
      "Moral-spiritual upbringing",
      "Sustainable economic growth based on innovation"
    ],
    "answer": "Sustainable economic growth based on innovation"
  },
  {
    "question": "A tradition to give a present to someone who has brought good news.",
    "options": [
      "Tolek",
      "Batyrlar",
      "Suinshi",
      "Zheruik"
    ],
    "answer": "Suinshi"
  },
  {
    "question": "The project initiated by the first President of Kazakhstan, aimed at sharing stories of successful Kazakhstani citizens.",
    "options": [
      "Bright Future of Kazakhstan",
      "Kazakhstan Talents",
      "Success Path",
      "100 new faces of Kazakhstan"
    ],
    "answer": "100 new faces of Kazakhstan"
  },
  {
    "question": "“Khan Shatyr” was built by plan of N. Foster.",
    "options": [
      "True",
      "False"
    ],
    "answer": "True"
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in culture are associated with the emergence of...",
    "options": [
      "Innovation",
      "Tradition",
      "Cultural Lag",
      "Isolation"
    ],
    "answer": "Innovation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Areas of implementation of the program 'Digital Kazakhstan' include ...",
    "options": [
      "Improving social services",
      "Environmental conservation",
      "Transition to a digital state",
      "Global partnerships"
    ],
    "answer": "Transition to a digital state"
  },
  {
    "question": "Everything is fantastic, and the differences between the origin culture and the new culture are hardly perceived, excused as defects in the loved person. To which stage does this description belong?",
    "options": [
      "Adaptation",
      "Rejection",
      "Frustration",
      "Honeymoon stage"
    ],
    "answer": "Honeymoon stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what stage of culture shock does one understand that the target culture is not bad, adapts to it, and starts developing routines?",
    "options": [
      "Initial Contact",
      "Crisis",
      "Disengagement",
      "Adjustment/Negotiation Stage"
    ],
    "answer": "Adjustment/Negotiation Stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Civilization is...",
    "options": [
      "A political structure of a society",
      "An economic framework",
      "A form of governance",
      "Material and spiritual culture of society at a certain historical stage of its development"
    ],
    "answer": "Material and spiritual culture of society at a certain historical stage of its development"
  },
  {
    "question": "A special project of the Rukhani Zhagyru program aimed at developing a 'small homeland,' engaging citizens in developing their native land, and addressing social issues.",
    "options": [
      "Cultural Revival",
      "National Development",
      "Land of Dreams",
      "Tugan zher"
    ],
    "answer": "Tugan zher"
  },
  {
    "question": "The general architectural plan of Astana was made by K. Kurokawa.",
    "options": [
      "True",
      "False"
    ],
    "answer": "True"
  },
  {
    "question": "The author of collections '1000 songs of the Kazakh people' and '500 Kazakh kyuis and songs' is A. Zataevich.",
    "options": [
      "True",
      "False"
    ],
    "answer": "True"
  },
  {
    "question": "Equal respect for various cultures and policies promoting cultural diversity without assimilation or segregation.",
    "options": [
      "Nationalism",
      "Multiculturalism",
      "Assimilation",
      "Cultural Fusion"
    ],
    "answer": "Multiculturalism"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term 'glocalisation' was introduced by...",
    "options": [
      "S. Huntington",
      "M. McLuhan",
      "A. Appadurai",
      "Robertson"
    ],
    "answer": "Robertson"
  },
  {
    "question": "Globalization is the idea about the formation and extension of relationships and interdependence of countries worldwide in various fields.",
    "options": [
      "True",
      "False"
    ],
    "answer": "True"
  },
  {
    "question": "The anxiety that results from losing familiar signs and symbols is...",
    "options": [
      "Acculturation",
      "Social Confusion",
      "Isolation",
      "Culture shock"
    ],
    "answer": "Culture shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following characteristics describe a Masculine Society?",
    "options": [
      "Gender equality",
      "Family orientation",
      "Emphasis on group harmony",
      "Work prevails over family"
    ],
    "answer": "Work prevails over family"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Hofstede model, short-term oriented countries are...",
    "options": [
      "Japan and South Korea",
      "India and China",
      "Italy and Spain",
      "U.S.A. and Australia"
    ],
    "answer": "U.S.A. and Australia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What percentage of seats in the Parliament of Kazakhstan is reserved for women?",
    "options": [
      "30%",
      "15%",
      "40%",
      "25%"
    ],
    "answer": "30%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Borrowing innovations from another culture occurs in the process of...",
    "options": [
      "Isolation",
      "Acculturation",
      "Assimilation",
      "Intercultural communication"
    ],
    "answer": "Intercultural communication"
  }
]

